Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Cinisomo, Mario, Undated, 1973 April 4 (Cassette 143, Box 2, Reel 143 (sides 1-2))
    Mario Cinisomo was born in 1913 in Brooklyn, New York to Italian immigrants. He worked as a longshoreman from 1932 until his retirement. He was a member of the International Longshoremen’s Association Local 1814, and held the position of Secretary-Treasurer at the time of the interview.
    One interview with Mario Cinisomo was conducted by Frank Farragaso at the International Longshoremen’s Association (ILA) Union Hall on Court Street in Brooklyn, New York. The date of the interview is unknown. A second interview was conducted by Leon Fink at the International Longshoremen's Association Union Hall on Court Street in Brooklyn, New York on April 4, 1973. The main topics of these interviews include the lives of Cinisomo’s parents; his employment prior to his involvement with the International Longshoremen's Association (ILA) Local 1814; social issues within the ILA; and social activities in which he participated outside of the ILA. Cinisomo discusses his father, including his positions as sergeant major in the Italian Navy and as a sailor on a Swedish merchant marine ship, and difficulties he had while working in the US due to his height, health issues, and illiteracy. He discusses his mother being a housewife; her work assisting other Italian immigrants in the United States (US) with their paperwork; and his parents’ arranged marriage in Italy. Cinisomo discusses his educational experiences, including graduating from public school; attending high school at night; and taking some college classes sponsored by the Works Progress Administration (WPA). He describes his employment before the ILA, including working in a laundry, a paper box factory, and as a grocery clerk, and his employment as an organizer in the WPA from the early 1930s until the start of World War II. He recalls social issues within the ILA, including the fact that the Irish and Germans controlled the union; that Italian workers were confined to working in the holds of the ships; and that striking was difficult because the Irish controlled the ILA and the police department. Cinisomo discusses leisure activities in which he participated, including attending church every Sunday; playing cards on his days off; and not playing sports because he was exhausted after his shifts.
    International Longshoremen's Association. Local 1814 (New York, N.Y.).; United States. Works Progress Administration (N.Y.).
  - Clanton, Elizabeth, 1975 October 24 (Cd ref33, ref33A, Box 6, Box 27)
    Elizabeth Clanton was born in Atmore, Alabama in 1901. Her grandparents were freed slaves and her father was a laborer on the railroad and in a saw mill. She married in 1920, had two sons, divorced, and remarried later in life. She worked in Illinois, Ohio, and California, before moving to New York, New York, where she worked as a nurses’ aid and was a member of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union.
    This interview was conducted by Leon Fink on October 24, 1975 at Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in Manhattan, New York. This interview covers Elizabeth Clanton’s childhood in Alabama; her migration throughout the United States (US); her work as a nurses’ aide; and her union activity. She begins by describing her childhood in Atmore, Alabama. She focuses on how Atmore was divided along racial lines, describing segregation in neighborhoods, schools, churches, and the movies; and the limited, strained social contact between members of the white and black communities. She also describes learning how to read in school, which enabled her to read the newspaper for her parents, neither of whom were literate. Other topics from her childhood include her close relationship with her father; some of her grandparents' history; leisure activities; holiday traditions; the type of music to which she listened; and her religious traditions and values.
    Clanton explains that it was typical for parents to decide who was an appropriate match for their daughters and describes the strict rules that governed interactions between young men and women. She describes meeting and marrying her first husband in Alabama despite her family’s reservations about her being too young and her occupation as a domestic worker for various families in Atmore, a position that she acquired from her mother when the latter became ill. She spends a great deal of time discussing her movement throughout the US, including moving to Cleveland, Ohio in order to find domestic work to support her children, whom she had left with her parents after she separated from her husband; receiving a certificate in practical nursing in Chicago, Illinois; and moving to Brooklyn, New York to live with one of her sons. She recalls sending much of the money she earned back to her family and writing letters to her mother and children to accompany each paycheck. Clanton discusses her union involvement, including being introduced to the idea of unions by organizer Jesse Olson while working at Beth Israel Hospital, as a nurses’ aide, in Manhattan; going to various hotels in New York City for union meetings; discussing union activities with co-workers only on breaks or after work; and participating in a hospital workers’ strike in 1959. Clanton discusses her opinion that despite the union not supporting striking workers sufficiently she realized the benefits of belonging to a union; her appreciation of Local 1199 after her retirement; and the educational programs and social activities that Local 1199 provided.
    Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union (New York, N.Y.).; African Americans |x Relations with Jews.; Cleveland (Ohio) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century.
  - Cohen, Arthur: Audio Recording, 1973 April 27 (Cassette 8, Box 22)
    Arthur Cohen was born in New York, New York around 1886 and was the youngest of seven sons. His father was a butcher on Hamilton Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. The family moved to the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan in 1891. Cohen attended the Hebrew Technical Institute and graduated as an electrician’s helper.
    This interview was conducted by Edmund Lake on April 27, 1973 at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York. It covers Arthur Cohen’s childhood, his work as an electrician, and his career as a semi-professional baseball player. Cohen discusses growing up in a predominantly Irish section of the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, in which his family was one of two Jewish families, and how his mother would be protected on her way home from local poker games by neighborhood ruffians. He describes his work at the Herring-Hall-Marvin Safe Company, attaching safe doors and setting the combinations. He describes his work as an electrician for industrial companies and being forced to leave this work due to his wife’s illness. He recounts his years playing baseball as a catcher and traveling with two teams, the Colonials and the Chambers Arrows.
    Electricians |z New York (State) |z New York.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) |x Ethnic relations.; Semi-professional baseball |z New York (State)
  - Cohen, Arthur: Transcript, 1973 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cohen, Rose: Audio Recording, 1973 March 30 (Box 22, Cassette 9, Box 1)
    Rose Cohen was born in Russia and was one of six children. She immigrated to the United States in 1912, where she worked in the garment industry. She was a member of the Socialist Party of America, the Workmen’s Circle, and an unspecified labor union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union).
    This interview was conducted by Wendy Fisher on March 30, 1973 at an unspecified location. The interview covers Rose Cohen’s early life and education in Russia, her immigration to the United States (US), her political activity, her working life, and her union activity. Cohen discusses her childhood in Russia, in particular, convincing her father to allow her to attend public school. She discusses immigrating to the US and living with her sisters on Orchard Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She discusses her first job in a shirtwaist factory; her attempts at unionizing the shop; and her attempts at recruiting workers into the Socialist Party of America. Other topics include brief histories of the Russian Revolution and the Workmen’s Circle and the importance of socialism in Cohen’s life.
    Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring.; Women socialists |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Cohen, Rose: Transcript, 1973 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Coker, Cora, 1974 April 25 (Cassette Missing)
  - Cole, Annie, 1975 November 13 (Cd ref37, Box 29)
    Annie Cole was born in Alabama in 1924. She graduated from the Tuskegee Institute with an associate degree in dietary health. She migrated to New York, New York and worked at Montefiore Hospital in the Bronx. She was a member of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union.
    This interview was conducted by Sasha Silverstein on November 13, 1975 at Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in Manhattan, New York. Topics of discussion include Annie Cole’s childhood, education, work experience, and union involvement. Cole briefly discusses her early life in Alabama and Texas; her education at the Tuskegee Institute; and the hardships she endured in attending college, including working long hours during the day and being too tired to study at night. She spends a majority of the interview discussing her working life, including a 6 month internship at an unspecified hospital on 125th street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and her job as a dietary aide at Montefiore Hospital in the Bronx, New York, which she began in 1952. She discusses in detail her reasons for joining Local 1199, including speaking with a strike organizer about her frustrations regarding taking on the work of the striking workers, in addition to her own. Cole discusses issues that she faced once she was a member of the union, including not receiving the same pay as hospital employees with different job titles, even though they did the same work, and unfair scheduling and benefits. She also discusses her struggles against management regarding workplace and pay discrimination throughout her career.
    Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union (New York, N.Y.).
  - Council Workshop for Senior Citizens I, Undated (Cassette 181 & 181A, Box 20)
    Danny Meeks was born in North Carolina and later migrated to New York, New York.
    Ponnie Johns was born in North Carolina and was one of six children. He later migrated to New York, New York.
    An unnamed female interviewee was born in Puerto Rico and migrated to New York, New York as a caretaker for children. She attended an unspecified school on 17th Street in Manhattan, New York but eventually returned to Puerto Rico where she married. She and her husband returned to New York in 1945 at behest of his family. She worked as a recordkeeper for the United States government.
    Mrs. Spornler was born in Romania and immigrated to the United States when she was 14 years old.
    Sedrkk Accent was born on the island of Saint Kitts in the West Indies. He worked as a machinist and was a professional boxer. He immigrated to the United States on August 2, 1963.
    Mrs. Haywood was born in Savannah, Georgia. She migrated to New York, New York after the death of her parents when she was six years old. She was one of eight children.
    Mrs. Switsky was born in New York, New York. Her parents were immigrants from Russia.
    This group interview was conducted by student interviewers Edmund Lake and Ron, only identified by his first name, and an unknown moderator. This interview contains a roundtable discussion with at least eight individuals who reflect on their immigration or migration to the United States (US) and New York, New York. The narrators tend to speak over one another, making it difficult to distinguish who is speaking; some narrators contribute more to the conversation than others; and the volume fluctuates throughout the interview.
    Topics covered in this interview include reasons for immigration or migration; family situations both before and after immigration or migration; living conditions in New York City, especially during the Great Depression; race relations within the US; jobs and working conditions; the comparison between New York City neighborhoods in the past and at the time of the interview; and student riots over rising college tuition costs at the time of the interview. The interview ends with the unknown moderator addressing the logistics of individual interviews for those who are interested.
    See also: Accent, Sedrkk; Johns, Ponnie; Meeks, Danny.
  - Council Workshop for Senior Citizens II, Undated (Cassette 180 & 180B, Box 20)
    Irene Fisil was born in New York, New York. Her parents immigrated to the United States from France.
    Mrs. Brooks was born in India and later immigrated to China after she was married. She immigrated to the United States when she was 58 years old.
    Mrs. Frank was born in Germany and immigrated to the United States when she was 40 years old.
    Clara Howard migrated from Virginia to New York, New York on April 3, 1912 when she was 16 years old.
    Mrs. Sunderman immigrated to the United States from Germany when she was 58 years old.
    Mrs. Small migrated from Virginia to New York, New York in 1920.
    Mr. Walters was born in Jamaica and immigrated to the United States with his parents when he was 21 years old.
    Mrs. Gordis immigrated to the United States from Russia when she was 25 years old. She worked in her sister’s store until she got married.
    This group interview was conducted by student interviewers, Edmund Lake and Karen Kearns, and an unknown moderator at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York. This interview consists of a roundtable discussion with at least eight individuals, who all reflect on their immigration or migration to the United States (US) and New York, New York. The narrators tend to speak over one another, making it difficult to distinguish who is speaking, and some narrators contribute more to the conversation than others.
    Topics covered in this interview include reasons for immigration or migration; family situations before and after immigration or migration; living conditions in New York, New York; native New Yorkers’ views of and relationships with the increasing immigrant population; race relations within the US; immigration journeys and conditions; jobs and working conditions; and the comparison between New York City neighborhoods in the past and at the time of the interview. The interview ends with the moderator addressing the logistics of individual interviews for those who are interested.
    See also: Howard, Clara; Sunderman, [Unknown]; Walters, [Unknown].
  - Council Workshop for Senior Citizens III, Undated (Cassette 180A & 180A.1, Box 20)
    Mr. Denberg was born in Winnipeg, Canada. His parents immigrated to Canada from Europe. The family immigrated to the United States after he was born and settled in New York, New York.
    Mrs. Fleekman was born in Austrian Galicia near the border of Austria and Russia.
    Rose Tannenbaum was born in Lithuania and immigrated to the United States when she was 12 years old.
    Mr. Hofsimmer was born in Galicia, Poland. He immigrated to the United States in 1911 when he was 20 years old in order to avoid being drafted into the Austrian Army. He worked as a sheet metal worker and mechanic and was a member of an unspecified union.
    Randy Summer was born in New York, New York and lived in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan.
    Mrs. Williams was born in St. Mathis, South Carolina and migrated to New York, New York when she was 25 years old.
    Mrs. Jasno was born in Russia.
    Mrs. Friedman was 28 years old when she immigrated to the United States from an unspecified country. She settled in New York, New York.
    Mr. Jackson migrated to New York, New York from Florida when he was 20 years old. He worked as a porter, shoe salesman, dishwasher, and waiter.
    Mrs. Fisher was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. She and her family moved to Atlantic City, New Jersey when she was three months old, and she moved to New York, New York when she was 25 years old.
    This group interview was conducted by student interviewers, John Jentz and Karen Kearns, and an unknown moderator at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York. This interview contains a roundtable discussion with at least ten individuals, all of whom provide a brief summary of where they were born and when they immigrated or migrated to the United States (US) or New York, New York. The narrators tend to speak over one another, making it difficult to distinguish who is speaking, and some narrators contribute more to the conversation than others. Topics covered in this interview include reasons for immigration or migration; family situations before and after immigration or migration; memories of Ellis Island; native New Yorkers’ views of and relationships with the increasing immigrant population; race relations within the US; a comparison of union and non-union jobs and conditions; and a comparison of the generations of the interviewers and the narrators. The interview ends with the moderator addressing the logistics of individual interviews for those who are interested.
    See also: Jackson, [unidentified]; and Tannenbaum, Rose.
  - Council Workshop for Senior Citizens IV, Undated (Cassette 182, Box 20)
    Ms. Chinsky was born in Manhattan, New York on East 49th Street. Her parents were Russian immigrants, and her father worked as a cabinet maker and antiquer. Her family moved often, usually in accordance with her father’s work, and lived in the Midtown and Harlem neighborhoods of Manhattan, New York and in the Bronx.
    Mr. Cone was born in New York, New York and worked as a locksmith.
    Mrs. Gren immigrated to the United States in July 1918 from the West Indies.
    Mr. O’Day was born in the Dominican Republic.
    Mrs. Ellis was born in Hungary.
    Mr. Fields was born in the Netherlands and raised in Austria. He immigrated to the United States in 1929.
    Mrs. Rappaport was born in Vilna, Poland. Her brother immigrated to the United States first, and the rest of the family followed and lived with him in Schenectady, New York. She later moved to 110th Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan.
    This group interview was conducted by student interviewers, John Jentz and Victor Scheluchin, and an unknown moderator at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street, Manhattan, New York. This interview contains a roundtable discussion with at least eight individuals, who reflect on their immigration or migration to the United States (US) and New York, New York. The narrators tend to speak over one another, making it difficult to distinguish who is speaking, and some narrators contribute more to the conversation than others. Topics covered in this interview include reasons for immigration/migration; family situations before and after immigration or migration; conditions during immigration, including memories of Ellis Island; native New Yorkers’ views of and relationships with the increasing immigrant population; race relations within the US and other countries; the comparison between union and non-union jobs and conditions; and the comparison between New York City neighborhoods in the past and at the time of the interview. The interview ends with the moderator addressing the logistics of individual interviews for those who were interested.
    See also: Fields, [unidentified].
  - Cowen, Maud, Undated (Box 18, Cd ref39)
    Maud Cowen was born in 1880 in Jamaica. She was the oldest of 12 children. Her mother managed the household while her father worked their farm. Cowen immigrated to the United States in 1916, settling in New York, New York. She held a number of jobs, including laborer in an ammunition factory during World War I; dressmaker; kosher cook; and as a maid and companion. She was married and had two daughters.
    The location, interviewer, and date of this interview are unknown. Topics include Maud Cowen’s childhood, her immigration to the United States (US), her first impressions of the US, her employment, and her family. Cowen recounts her early life in Jamaica including her large family; her father owning a farm and her recollection of shipping oranges in barrels and raising animals; and teaching herself how to make dresses. She recounts immigration officials in the US not wanting Cowen to leave with her black cousin when she arrived in New York, New York. Cowen discusses her negative first impressions of the US, including feeling out of place and crying every night; feeling that people were unfriendly; and that she never had enough money. She recalls the US attempting to deport her to Jamaica or Great Britain during World War I and fighting the deportation. Cowan discusses her employment, including working at an ammunition factory in New Jersey; working in a laundry pressing soldiers’ uniforms; sewing dresses as part of a display in a shop window in the Garment District neighborhood of Manhattan; working as a kosher cook; and being a maid and companion in a hospital. Cowen discusses her kosher cooking, including learning the skill from a friendly Jewish woman for whom she worked; cooking for individuals as well as catering parties; and leaving this line of work after being severely burned lighting an oven. She discusses her daughters in detail, including the fact that they were both well educated and married, that both wanted her to move back to Jamaica at the time of the interview; and that one daughter owns 40 acres of land with a large house and a maid.
    See also: Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York,New York and the United States; and Neighborhood.
  - Cramer, Paul: Audio Recording, 1973 April 2 (Cassette 10, Box 22)
    Paul Cramer was born in 1876 in Germany. He was a member of the German merchant marine. He held a number of jobs after his immigration to the United States, including furnace maintainer, grocery clerk, gardener, and window cleaner. He married twice and had two children with his first wife.
    This interview was conducted on April 2, 1973 by Kathleen Gimblet at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York. The interview covers Paul Cramer’s working life in Germany and the United States (US) and his personal life. Cramer discusses being drafted into the German Army in 1890; joining the German merchant marine two years later; and traveling to Australia and Japan in the merchant marine before immigrating to the US. He briefly mentions his first marriage before discussing his second marriage to a woman who had been a vaudevillian. He describes his work maintaining furnaces in 13 houses in Manhattan, New York. Cramer also describes working as a butler in Lake George, New York; making good money as a window cleaner; and finding work at unemployment offices and through window advertisements.
    Germans |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Cramer, Paul: Transcript, 1973 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Crupi, Caroline: Audio Recording, 1974 May 8 (Cassette 158, Box 7 & 21)